Donald F. Moss Papers VHP2005/18
CCSU Veterans History Project
Donald F. Moss Papers
Bulk, 1942-1946
1942 - 1946, 2005
VHP2005/18
CCSU Veterans History Project
260.0 Digital objects 1 interview
The collection details Donald F. Moss's experience when he was serving in United States Marine Corps during World War II. Materials in the collection include oral history interview, WWII related drawing, memoirs, and photographs.
Moss, Donald F., 1920 -
Biographical/Historical note
Donald Moss joined the U.S. Marine Corps in February of 1942, shortly after the attack on Pearl Harbor. At the time he had just finished art school in Boston, MA, and was working for a printing company. He attended basic training at Parris Island, SC, where he described the training as very rigorous. Moss then went to Guadalcanal, where he and others would go on patrols in enemy territory to scout out the placement of enemy troops. After the intense battle that took place in Guadalcanal, the Marines were sent on a 30-day furlough in Melbourne, Australia, and then sent on to Guam. Moss continued working for regimental intelligence in Guam, drawing battle maps for the invasion of Japan, which he did for the duration of the war. While there, he also made prints of his painting of the Battle of Guadalcanal, of which he sold hundreds of copies. It was also in Guam, where Moss worked under Capt. Gene Davis, who would later assist Moss with finding free-lance work with Colliers magazine after the war. He returned home when the war ended, but was not discharged until March of 1946. After his discharge he moved to New York City, where he went to Pratt Institute, and later became an illustrator for Sports Illustrated Magazine. Moss painted scenes from the Lake Placid Olympics and champion golf courses, among other things, which he did for 30 years, until his semi-retirement in 1984. He also became the Chairman and Vice President of the Society of Illustrators, Air Force Arts Program, a program that enabled military artists to travel throughout the world. Moss painted a number of scenes associated with this program, some of which are now hanging in the Pentagon.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
United States. Marine Corps. Marines, 1st. Battalion, 3rd..; United States. Marine Corps.; Drawing (image-making); Guadalcanal (Solomon Islands); Guadalcanal, Battle of, Solomon Islands, 1942-1943; Guam; Interviews; Manuscript; New Britain Island (Papua New Guinea); Parris Island (S.C.); Photographs; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2005/18.I
  - Painting of crashed Japanese's Mitsubishi G4M bomber (the "Betty") and four Lockheed P-38 Lightning, American fighter aircraft., 1994; VHP2005/18.I.1
    General note
    Donald Moss was commissioned to paint in 1994 (5oth Anniversary of Pacific War)
  - "Hell Point 'Battle on Mid-Northern Coast of Guadalcanal'" Poster, 1943; VHP2005/18.I.2; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Flyer from the War Memorial Foundation, VHP2005/18.I.3
  - Guadalcanal American Memorial flyer, n.d.; VHP2005/18.I.4
    Donald Moss’s painting of the representation of the Guadalcanal American Memorial. Prints of Don’s painting were sold to raise funds for the construction of the monument.
  - Donald Moss’s article on the Battle of the Tenaru Guadalcanal, 1942, after June 1992; VHP2005/18.I.5
  - "What was it like in the olden days, Dad?" Donoald Moss's unpublished Memoir, Between 2001 - 2005; VHP2005/18.I.6; 247.0 Digital objects
  - Interview synopsis, Nov. 3, 2005; VHP2005/18.I.7; 247.0
- Series II: Publications, VHP2005/18.II
  - "Donald Moss Remembers Guadalcanal Battle 50 Years Later" Article on Donald’s painting of the Memorial of Guadalcanal Battle, circa 1990s; VHP2005/18.II.1; 247.0
  - "Donald Moss Remembers Guadalcanal Battle 50 Years Later" (continued), circa 1990s; VHP2005/18.II.2; 247.0
  - Story on the Battle of Guadalcanal and his painting in the Old Breed News magazine, October 1998; VHP2005/18.II.3; 247.0
  - "Voices of Connecticut Veterans: Donald Moss and an Artist’s Vision of War" by Judi Houpert, 2006; VHP2005/18.II.4; 5.0 pages; Judi Houpert
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2005/18.III
  - Oral history interview, Nov. 3, 2005; VHP2005/18.III.1; 1.0 dvd; Judi Houpert (Disk DVD VHP2005/18, Box VHP Interview #1)